An 18-year-old, African-American male joined the United States Air Force
في الثامنة عشر من عمره، أمريكي من أصل افريقي انضم الى القوات الجوية الامريكية
and was assigned to Mountain Home Air Force Base
و تم بعثه الى قاعدة سلاح الجو في "ماونتن هوم"
and was a part of the air police squadron.
وكان جزءا من سرب شرطة الطائرات.
Upon first arriving there, the first goal that I had
عقب وصولي هناك، الهدف الاول الذي كان لدي
was for me to identify an apartment,
هو ان ابحث عن شقة،
so I could bring my wife and my new baby, Melanie,
لاستطيع ان اجلب زوجتي و طفلتي الجديدة، ميلاني،
out to join me in Idaho.
لكي نجتمع معا في "ايداهو".
I immediately went to the personnel office,
ذهبت فورا الى مكتب الموظفين،
and talking with the guys in personnel,
و تحدثت الى الشباب في مكتب الموظفين،
they said, "Hey, no problem finding an apartment in Mountain Home, Idaho.
قالوا: "لا يوجد مشكلة في العثور على شقة في (ماونتن هوم، ايداهو).
The people down there love us because they know if they have an airman
الناس هناك يحبونا لأنهم يعلمون انه اذا كان لديهم طيار
who is coming in to rent one of their apartments,
يريد ان يستأجر شقة من شققهم،
they'll always get their money."
فسيحصلون دائما على اموالهم."
And that was a really important thing.
و كان هذا شيء مهم حقاً.
He said, "So here is a list of people that you can call,
قال: " هذه لائحة من الاشخاص تستطيع الاتصال بهم،
and then they will then allow you to select the apartment that you want."
و عندها سيسمحون لك باختيار الشقة التي تريدها."
So I got the list; I made the call.
لذا حصلت على اللائحة، أجريت الاتصال.
The lady answered on the other end and I told her what I wanted.
أجابت السيدة و قلت لها ما اريده.
She said, "Oh, great you called.
قالت: " اوه، جيد انك اتصلت.
We have four or five apartments available right now."
لدينا اربعة او خمس شقق متوفرة حاليا."
She said, "Do you want a one-bedroom or two-bedroom?"
قالت: " اتريد غرفة نوم ام غرفتي نوم ؟"
Then she said, "Let's not talk about that.
ثم قالت: " دعنا لا نتحدث بخصوص هذا.
Just come on down, select the apartment that you want.
تعال الى هنا، اختر الشقة التي تريدها.
We'll sign the contract
و سنوقع العقد.
and you'll have keys in your hand to get your family out here right away."
و ستحصل على المفاتيح بيدك لكي تجلب عائلتك فورا."
So I was excited.
لذا كنت متحمسا.
I jumped in my car. I went downtown and knocked on the door.
أسرعت الى سيارتي. ذهبت الى مركز المدينة و طرقت على الباب.
When I knocked on the door, the woman came to the door,
عندما طرقت على الباب، السيدة جاءت الى الباب،
and she looked at me, and she said, "Can I help you?"
و نظرت الي، وقالت: "هل استطيع مساعدتك؟"
I said, "Yes, I'm the person who called about the apartments.
قلت: "نعم، انا الشخص الذي اتصل بك بخصوص الشقق.
I was just coming down to make my selection."
جئت الى هنا لاختار الشقة."
She said, "You know what? I'm really sorry,
قالت: "اتدري؟ انا اسفة جدا،
but my husband rented those apartments and didn't tell me about them."
لكن زوجي أجّر تلك الشقق و لم يخبرني بشأنهم."
I said, "You mean he rented all five of them in one hour?"
قلت: "أتعنين انه أجر الشقق الخمسة في ساعة واحدة ؟"
She didn't give me a response, and what she said was this:
لم تعطني جوابا، و ما قالته بخصوص هذا:
She said, "Why don't you leave your number,
قالت: " لم لا تترك لي رقمك،
and if we have some openings, I'll give you a call?"
واذا كان لدينا بعض الشقق، سأتصل بك ؟
Needless to say, I did not get a call from her.
غني عن القول، انني لم أحصل على اتصال منها.
Nor did I get any responses from the other people
و لم احصل على ردود من باقي الناس
that they gave me on the list where I could get apartments.
الذين كانوا موجودين على اللائحة التي استطيع من خلالها الحصول على شقة.
So as a result of that, and feeling rejected,
لذا كنتيجة لهذا، و لشعوري بأنني مرفوض
I went back to the base, and I talked to the squadron commander.
عدت الى القاعدة، و تحدثت الى قائد السرب.
His name was McDow, Major McDow.
اسمه كان "ماكدو"، الرائد "ماكدو".
I said, "Major McDow, I need your help."
قلت: "ايها الرائد ماكدو، احتاج مساعدتك."
I told him what happened, and here's what he said to me:
و اخبرته ما حدث، و هذا ما قاله لي:
He said, "James, I would love to help you.
قال: "جيمس، أحب أن اساعدك.
But you know the problem:
و لكن تعلم ما هي المشكلة:
We can't make people rent to folks that they don't want to rent to.
لا نستطيع ارغام الناس على تأجير شققهم الى أشخاص لا يريدونهم.
And besides, we have a great relationship with people in the community
و الى جانب هذا، لدينا علاقات رائعة مع الناس في المجتمع هنا
and we really don't want to damage that."
و لا نريد حقا ان نلحق الضرر بهذا."
He said, "So maybe this is what you should do.
قال: "لذا ربما هذا ما يجب عليك فعله.
Why don't you let your family stay home,
لم لا تترك عائلتك تظل في مسقط رأسك،
because you do know that you get a 30-day leave.
لأنك تعلم انك تحصل على 30 يوم اجازة.
So once a year,
لذا مرة في السنة،
you can go home to your family, spend 30 days and then come on back."
تستطيع الذهاب الى منزل عائلتك، تقضي 30 يوما ثم تعود هنا."
Needless to say, that didn't resonate for me.
غني عن القول، أن هذا لم يكن مناسبا لي.
So after leaving him, I went back to personnel,
لذا بعد ان تركته، ذهبت مجددا الى مكتب الموظفين،
and talking to the clerk,
و تحدثت الى الكاتب هناك،
he said, "Jim, I think I have a solution for you.
قال: "جيم، أظن أن لدي حلا لك
There's an airman who is leaving and he has a trailer.
هناك طيار مغادر و لديه مقطورة.
If you noticed, in Mountain Home,
اذا لاحظت في "ماونتن هوم".
there are trailer parks and trailers all over the place.
هناك مواقف للمقطورات و مقطورات في كل الانحاء.
You can buy his trailer, and you'd probably get a really good deal
تستطيع شراء هذه المقطورة، و ربما تحصل على عرض جيد حقا
because he wants to get out of town as soon as possible.
لأنه يريد الخروج من البلدة بأسرع وقت ممكن.
And that would take care of your problem,
و هذا سيكون كفيلا بحل مشاكلك،
and that would provide the solution for you."
و هذا سيوفر الحل لك."
So I immediately jumped in my car, went downtown, saw the trailer --
لذا اسرعت فورا الى سيارتي، ذهبت الى مركز المدينة، رأيت المقطورة --
it was a small trailer,
كانت مقطورة صغيرة،
but under the circumstances,
و لكن في تلك الظروف،
I figured that was the best thing that I could do.
أدركت ان هذا سيكون أفضل شيء استطيع فعله.
So I bought the trailer.
لذا اشتريت المقطورة.
And then I asked him, "Can I just leave the trailer here,
ثم سألته: "هل أستطيع ترك المقطورة هنا،
and that would take care of all my problems,
و هذا سيكون مناسبا لحل كل مشاكلي،
I wouldn't have to find another trailer park?"
و لن اضطر للبحث عن موقف مقطورة آخر؟"
He said, "Before I say yes to that, I need to check with management."
قال: "قبل ان اقول نعم لهذا، يجب ان ابحث الأمر مع الادارة."
So I get back to the base,
لذا عدت الى القاعدة،
he called me back and management said,
اتصل بي و اخبرني ان الادارة قالت:
"No, you can't leave the trailer here
"لا، لا تستطيع ترك المقطورة هنا
because we had promised that slot to some other people."
لاننا وعدنا أشخاص آخرون بهذا المكان".
And that was strange to me
و هذا كان غريبا بالنسبة لي
because there were several other slots that were open,
لأنه كان هناك عدة أماكن أخرى متوفرة
but it just so happened that he had promised that slot to someone else.
و لكن حدث انه وعد بهذا المكان الى شخص آخر.
So, what I did --
لذا، ما فعلته --
and he said, "You shouldn't worry, Jim, because there are a lot of trailer parks."
و قال: "لا تقلق جيم، لأن هناك الكثير من مواقف المقطورات."
So I put out another exhaustive list of going to trailer parks.
لذا وضعت لائحة أخرى متعبة للذهاب الى مواقف المقطورات.
I went to one after another, after another.
ذهبت الى واحدة تلو الأخرى، تلو أخرى،
And I got the same kind of rejection there
و تلقيت ذات الرفض هناك
that I received when I was looking for the apartment.
الذي تلقيته عندما كنت ابحث عن شقق.
And as a result, the kind of comments that they made to me,
و كنتيجة، نفس نوع التعلقيات التي كانوا يقولونها لي.
in addition to saying that they didn't have any slots open,
بالاضافة لقولهم انهم لم يعد لديهم أماكن متوفرة،
one person said, "Jim, the reason why we can't rent to you,
شخص قال: " جيم، سبب عدم قدرتنا ايجارك المكان،
we already have a Negro family in the trailer park."
انه لدينا مسبقا عائلة زنجية في موقف المقطورات."
He said, "And it's not me, because I like you people."
قال: "الامر لا يتعلق بي، أنا أحبكم يا قوم."
(Laughs)
(ضحك)
And that's what I did, too. I chuckled, too.
و هذا ما فعلته ايضا، ذهلت ايضا
He said, "But here's the problem:
قال: " ولكن هنا المشكلة
If I let you in, the other tenants will move out
اذا سمحت لكم بالبقاء هنا، المستأجرون الآخرون سيرغمونكم على الرحيل
and I can't afford to take that kind of a hit."
و لا استطيع ان اتحمل ان اقوم بهذه المجازفة."
He said, "I just can't rent to you."
قال: "لا أستطيع تأجيرك المكان."
Even though that was discouraging, it didn't stop me.
بالرغم من ان هذا كان غير مشجع، لم يوقفني.
I kept looking,
استمريت بالبحث،
and I looked at the far end of the town in Mountain Home,
و بحثت في أقصى مدينة "ماونتن هوم"،
and there was a small trailer park.
و كان هناك موقف مقطورات صغير،
I mean, a really small trailer park.
و أعني موقف مقطورات صغير جدا.
it didn't have the concrete slabs,
لم تكن تحوي الواح خرسانة،
it didn't have fencing
لم تكن تحوي سياج
to portion off your trailer slot from other trailer slots.
لتفصل بين مقطورتك عن المقطورات الآخريات.
It didn't have a laundry facility.
لم تكن تحوي منشأة لغسيل الثياب.
But the conclusion I reached at that moment
و لكن النتيجة التي توصلت اليها ذلك الوقت
was that I didn't have a lot of other options.
هو انني لم اكن املك الكثير من الخيارات.
So I called my wife, and I said, "We're going to make this one work."
لذا اتصلت بزوجتي، وقلت: " سوف نقوم بانجاح هذا الأمر."
And we moved into it
و انتقلنا الى هناك
and we became homeowners in Mountain Home, Idaho.
و أصبحنا من أصحاب المنازل في ماونتن هوم، ايداهو.
And of course, eventually things settled down.
و بالطبع، في النهاية استقرت الأمور.
Four years after that, I received papers to move from Mountain Home, Idaho
بعد اربع سنوات، استلمت اوراقا للانتقال من ماونتن هوم، ايداهو
to a place called Goose Bay, Labrador.
الى مكان يدعى "غوز باي، لابرادور".
We won't even talk about that. It was another great location. (Laughter)
لن نتحدث حتى عن هذا. كان مكان رائع آخر. (ضحك)
So my challenge then was to get my family from Mountain Home, Idaho
لذا التحدي لدي كان لنقل عائلتي من ماونت هوم، ايداهو
to Sharon, Pennsylvania.
الى شارون، بنسلفانيا.
That wasn't a problem because we had just purchased a brand-new automobile.
هذا لم يكن مشكلة لأننا كنا قد اشترينا مؤخرا سيارة جديدة.
My mother called and said she'll fly out.
اتصلت أمي و قالت انها ستأتي ايضا.
She'll be with us as we drive, she'll help us manage the children.
ستكون معنا خلال رحلتنا، ستساعدنا عبر الاهتمام بالاطفال.
So she came out, her and Alice put a lot of food together for the trip.
لذا جاءت، هي و اليس وضعوا كمية طعام كبيرة للرحلة.
That morning, we left at about 5 a.m.
ذلك الصباح، ذهبنا الساعة الخامسة صباحا.
Great trip, having a great time, good conversation.
رحلة رائعة، قضينا وقت ممتع، أحاديث جيدة.
Somewhere around 6:30, 7 o'clock, we got a little bit tired,
و في وقت ما بين الساعة السادسة و النصف و السابعة تعبنا قليلا،
and we said, "Why don't we get a motel so that we can rest
و قلنا: " لم لا نحصل على غرفة في فندق صغير لكي نرتاح
and then have an early start in the morning?"
ثم ننهض باكرا لنكمل الرحلة في الصباح؟"
So we were looking at a number of the motels as we drove down the road,
لذا بحثنا في عدد من الفنادق الصغيرة
and we saw one, it was a great big, bright flashing light that said,
و وجدنا واحد، كان له انارة كبيرة جدا تقول:
"Vacancies, Vacancies, Vacanies."
"شواغر، شواغر، شواغر."
So we stopped in.
لذا توقفنا عنده.
They were in the parking lot, I went inside.
كانوا في مساحة الموقف، انا ذهبت الى الداخل
When I walked inside,
عندما مشيت الى الداخل،
the lady was just finishing up one contract with some folks,
السيدة كانت قد انهت توا عقد مع بعض الاشخاص،
some other people were coming in behind me.
بعض الاشخاص الآخرين كانوا يدخلون خلفي.
And so I walked to the counter,
فمشيت الى شباك الحجز،
and she said, "How can I help you?"
و قالت: "كيف استطيع خدمتك؟"
I said, "I would like to get a motel for the evening for my family."
قلت: "اود ان احصل على غرفة مساء من اجل عائلتي."
She said, "You know, I'm really sorry, I just rented the last one.
قالت: "أتدري، انا اسفة جدا، لقد أجرت آخر غرفة الآن.
We will not have any more until the morning."
لن نؤجر اي غرفة حتى الصباح."
She said, "But if you go down the road about an hour, 45 minutes,
قالت: " و لكن اذا اتجهت اسفل الطريق، حوالي 45 دقيقة،
there's another trailer park down there."
يوجد هناك موقف مقطورة آخر."
I said, "Yeah, but you still have the 'Vacancies' light on, and it's flashing."
قلت: " لكن ما زال الضوء يومئ "شواغر" و هو ما مازال يومض."
She said, "Oh, I forgot."
قالت: "آه نسيت"
And she reached over and turned the light off.
ثم ذهبت و أطفأت الضوء.
She looked at me and I looked at her.
نظرت الي و نظرت اليها.
There were other people in the room.
كان هناك اشخاص آخرون في الغرفة.
She kind of looked at them. No one said anything.
نظرت اليهم بطريقة ما. لم يقل احد شيئا.
So I just got the hint and I left, and went outside to the parking lot.
لذا فهمت التلميج و ذهبت، و مشيت خارجاً الى مساحة الموقف.
And I told my mother and I told my wife and also Melanie, and I said,
و اخبرت أمي و اخبرت زوجتي و ميلاني ايضا، وقلت:
"It looks like we're going to have to drive a little bit further down the road
" يبدو انه علينا ان نقود قليلا أكثر في الطريق
to be able to sleep tonight."
لنستطيع النوم الليلة."
And we did drive down the road,
و بالفعل قدنا في الطريق،
but just before we took off and pulled out of the parking lot,
و لكن قبل ان نغادر مساحة الموقف،
guess what happened?
احزروا ماذا حدث؟
The light came back on.
عاد الضوء للعمل.
And it said, "Vacancies, Vacancies, Vacancies."
و كان يقول: "شواغر، شواغر، شواغر."
We were able to find a nice place.
استطعنا ان نجد مكانا لطيفا.
It wasn't our preference, but it was secure and it was clean.
لم يكن المفضل لدينا، لكنه كان آمنا و كان نظيفا.
And so we had a great sleep that night.
لذا حصلنا على نوم هانئ تلك الليلة.
The piece that's important about that
الجزء المهم فيما يتعلق بهذا
is that we had similar kinds of experiences
هو انه كان لدينا تجارب مماثلة من هذا النوع
from Idaho all the way through to Pennsylvania,
من ايداهو كل الطريق نحو بنسلفانيا.
where we were rejected from hotels, motels and restaurants.
حيث تم رفضنا من الفنادق، الفنادق الصغيرة، و المطاعم.
But we made it to Pennsylvania.
و لكننا وصلنا الى بنسلفانيا.
We got the family settled. Everyone was glad to see the kids.
استقرت العائلة، و الكل كان سعيدا لرؤية الأطفال.
I jumped on a plane and shot off to Goose Bay, Labrador,
ركبت في طائرة و غادرت الى غوز باي، لابرادور،
which is another story, right?
و هي قصة أخرى، اليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here it is, 53 years later,
الآن هنا، بعد 53 عاما،
I now have nine grandchildren, two great-grandchildren.
الآن لدي تسع أحفاد، ولدين من أحفادي.
Five of the grandchildren are boys.
خمسة من احفادي صبيان.
I have master's, Ph.D., undergrad, one in medical school.
لدي ماستر، دكتوراه، غير متخرج، واحد منهم في كلية الطب.
I have a couple that are trending.
لدي اثنان يتوجهان نحو ذلك.
They're almost there but not quite. (Laughter)
هم قريبين من ذلك لكن ليس تماما. (ضحك)
I have one who has been in college now for eight years.
عندي واحد كان في الثانوية لثماني سنوات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He doesn't have a degree yet, but he wants to be a comedian.
ليس لديه شهادة بعد، لكنه يريد ان يصبح ممثل هزلي.
So we're just trying to get him to stay in school.
لذا نحن نريده ان يبقى في المدرسة.
Because you never know,
لأنك لا تعلم أبدا ما يحصل،
just because you're funny at home, does not make you a comedian, right?
فقط لكونك مضحك في المنزل، لا يجعلك ممثل هزلي، اليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the thing about it, they're all good kids --
لكن ما يهم في هذا، هم جميعهم أطفال صالحون --
no drugs, no babies in high school, no crime.
لا مخدرات، لا أطفال في الثانوية، لا جريمة.
So with that being the backdrop,
اذا مع أخذ هذا في عين الاعتبار،
I was sitting in my TV room watching TV,
كنت جالسا في غرفة التلفاز، أتفرج عليه،
and they were talking about Ferguson and all the hullabaloo that was going on.
و كانوا يتحدثون عن "فيرغوسن" و كل الضوضاء التي كانت موجودة.
And all of a sudden, one of the news commentators got on the air and she said,
و فجأة، واحدة من معلقي الأخبار كان على الهواء، وقالت:
"In the last three months,
" في الثلاث الشهور الأخيرة،
eight unarmed African-American males
ثماني امريكيين من اصول افريقية غير مسلحين
have been killed by police, white homeowners, or white citizens."
تم قتلهم من قبل الشرطة، أصحاب منازل بيض البشرة، او مواطنين بيض."
For some reason, at that moment it just all hit me.
لسبب ما في تلك اللحظة كل شي ورد الى ذهني
I said, "What is it? It is so insane.
قلت: "ما هذا؟ هذا جنون.
What is the hatred that's causing people to do these kinds of things?"
ما هذه الكراهية التي تدفع الناس الى اقتراف مثل هذه الافعال؟"
Just then, one of my grandsons called.
حينها فقط، احد احفادي اتصل.
He said, "Granddad, did you hear what they said on TV?"
قال: "جدي، هل سمعت ما قالوه على التلفاز؟"
I said, "Yes, I did."
قلت: "نعم ، سمعت".
He said, "I'm just so confused.
قال: " انا مرتبك كثيرا.
We do everything we do, but it seems that driving while black,
نفعل كل ما نفعله، و لكن يبدون ان القيادة عندما نكون سود،
walking while black, talking while black, it's just dangerous.
المشي و نحن سود، التكلم و نحن سود، هو خطير فقط.
What can we do? We do everything that you told us to do.
ماذا نستطيع ان نفعل؟ نفعل كل ما قلته لنا.
When stopped by the police,
عندما توقفنا الشرطة.
we place both hands on the steering wheel at the 12 o'clock position.
نضع اليدين فوق المقود في وضعية الساعة12.
If asked to get identification,
اذا سُئلنا عن الهوية،
we tell them, 'I am slowly reaching over into the glove compartment to get my I.D.'
نقول لهم: " انا اتحرك ببطء لآخذ الهوية من صندوق السيارة الامامي"
When pulled out of the car to be searched,
عندما نوقف خارج السيارة من اجل تفتيشنا.
when laid on the ground to be searched,
عندما ننبطح من اجل تفتيشنا،
when our trunks are opened to be searched,
عندما تفتح سياراتنا ليتم تفتيشها،
we don't push back, we don't challenge because we know, you've told us,
لا نصدهم، لا نتحدى لأننا نعلم، لانك قلت لنا،
'Don't you challenge the police.
لا تتحدوا الشرطة.
After it's over, call us and we'll be the ones to challenge."
بعد ان ينتهي كل هذا، اتصل بنا و سنكون الاشخاص الذين يتحدون."
He said, "And this is the piece that really bugs me:
قال: " وهذا الشيء الذي يزعجني حقاً:
Our white friends, our buddies, we kind of hang together.
أصدقاؤنا البيض، أصحابنا، نحن نخرج سوية.
When they hear about these kinds of things happening to us, they say,
عندما يسمعون بهذه الاشياء التي تحدث لنا، يقولون:
'Why do you take it?
" لم تقبلون بهذا؟
You need to push back. You need to challenge.
يجب عليكم ان تصدوا يجب عليكم ان تتحدوا
You need to ask them for their identification.'"
يجب عليكم ان تسألوهم عن هوياتهم."
And here's what the boys have been taught to tell them:
و هذا ما تعلم الصبية ان يجيبوهم به :
"We know that you can do that, but please do not do that
" نحن نعلم أنكم تستطيعون فعل هذا، و لكن رجاء لا تفعلوا هذا.
while we're in the car
بينما نحن في السيارة
because the consequences for you are significantly different
لأن نتائج هذا بالنسبة لكم هي مختلفة بشكل كبير
than the consequences for us."
عن نتائجها بالنسبة لنا."
And so as a grandparent, what do I tell my grandsons?
و كجدّ، ماذا أقول لأحفادي؟
How do I keep them safe? How do I keep them alive?
كيف أبقيهم آمنين؟ كيف أبقيهم أحياء؟
As a result of this, people have come to me and said,
كنتيجة لهذا، الناس قدموا الي و قالوا:
"Jim, are you angry?"
"جيم، هل أنت غاضب؟"
And my response to that is this:
و جوابي على هذا كان:
"I don't have the luxury of being angry,
" ليس لدي رفاهية أن أكون غاضبا،
and I also know the consequences of being enraged."
و ايضا انا اعلم نتائج انا اكون غاضبا."
So therefore, the only thing that I can do
بالتالي، إن الشيء الوحيد الذي استطيع فعله
is take my collective intellect and my energy and my ideas and my experiences
هو أن آخذ فكري الجماعي و طاقتي و أفكاري و تجاربي
and dedicate myself to challenge, at any point in time,
و أكرس نفسي للتحدي، في اي لحظة من الوقت،
anything that looks like it might be racist.
اي شيء قد يبدو كأنه عنصري.
So the first thing I have to do is to educate,
لذا اول شيء علي فعله هو أن أعلّم،
the second thing I have to do is to unveil racism,
ثاني شيء علي فعله هو أن أكشف النقاب عن العنصرية،
and the last thing I need to do is do everything within my power
و آخر شيء علي فعله هو أن أفعل كل ما بوسعي
to eradicate racism in my lifetime by any means necessary.
هو القضاء على العنصرية في حياتي بكل الوسائل الضرورية.
The second thing I do is this:
ثاني شيء أفعله هو التالي:
I want to appeal to Americans.
أريد أن أناشد الأمريكيين.
I want to appeal to their humanity, to their dignity,
أريد أن أناشد إنسانيتهم، كرامتهم،
to their civic pride and ownership
فخرهم المدني و
to be able to not react to these heinous crimes in an adverse manner.
لكي يكون من الممكن عدم الرد على هذه الجرائم الشنيعة بطريقة عكسية.
But instead, to elevate your level of societal knowledge,
لكن بدلا عن ذلك، ان ترفع مستوى معرفتك المجتمعية،
your level of societal awareness and societal consciousness
مستوى وعيك المجتمعي و ضميرك المجتمعي
to then collectively come together, all of us come together,
لنأتي كلنا معاً، بشكل جماعي و مع بضعنا البعض،
to make sure that we speak out against and we challenge any kind of insanity,
لنتأكد من أننا نتكلم علنا ضد هذا و نتحدى كل نوع من انواع الجنون،
any kind of insanity that makes it okay to kill unarmed people,
اي نوع من الجنون الذي يجعل من الصحيح قتل ناس غير مسلحين.
regardless of their ethnicity,
بغض النظر عن أصولهم،
regardless of their race,
بغض النظر عن عرقهم،
regardless of their diversity makeup.
بغض النظر عن تنوعهم.
We have to challenge that. It doesn't make any sense.
يجب ان نتحدى هذا، هذا ليس فيه منطق.
The only way I think we can do that is through a collective.
الطريقة الوحيدة التي أظن أننا نستطيع تحقيق هذا عن طريق التعاون.
We need to have black and white and Asian and Hispanic
يجب أن يوجد سود و بيض آسيويين و لاتينيين
just to step forward and say,
ليتقدموا و يقولوا: